Guide to the Manuel Ruiz Papers, 1931-1986
Department of Special Collections
Manuel Ruiz Papers,
1931-1986
Special Collections M0295
Manuel, Ruiz
13.25 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Gift of Manuel Ruiz, Jr., 1978-1986.
ABSTRACT
Correspondence, minutes, agendas, reports, articles, notes, statements, newsclippings, financial records, and photographs. The papers document Ruiz's participation in Cultura Panamericana, Inc. and the Coordinating Committee for Latin American Youth during the 1940s, and the Mexican American Political Association and War on Poverty, Inc. during the 1960s. Also included are subject files on civil rights, Mexican Americans and education, police-community relations, and administration of justice. Primarily in English, with some material in Spanish.
BIOGRAPHY
Manuel Ruiz, Jr. was born in Los Angeles on July 25, 1905. He and his parents, who had come to Southern California from Mazatlan, Mexico, resided in the Belvedere Gardens section of East Los Angeles. Ruiz graduated from Manual Arts High School in 1923 where he distinguished himself as captain of the track and debate teams, concert master of the school orchestra, and class valedictorian. At the University of Southern California in Los Angeles, he continued his participation in track and debate; he also joined Sigma Phi Epsilon, a social fraternity, and Gamma Eta Gamma, a legal fraternity. He received the A.B. in law in 1927 and the L.L.B. (graduate law degree) in 1930. Ruiz was admitted to the practice of law in California that same year. In an interview conducted in 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9), Ruiz recalled that racial prejudice kept him from joining an established Los Angeles firm, "Fortunately for me I was not acceptable in a regular law firm although I had good grades --I was almost a straight A student --I had to start a law practice on my own." He rented a two-room, forty dollar a month office, and did his own secretarial work. Ruiz pursued a specialty in international private law and was admitted to the Bar in Chihuahua, Mexico, in 1932. Later his brother, Alexander, became a member of the firm. Ruiz sought to join the Federal Bureau of Investigation to do undercover war work in Latin America, but instead he spent the World War II years in Los Angeles as a community organizer and activist. The firm belief that friendship and solidarity among the American republics was integral to the Allied Forces' war efforts led Ruiz to become a founding member and executive secretary of Cultura Panamericana, Inc. in 1940. The goals of the 1,000 member group included the promotion of interest in inter-American culture and cultural exchange, support for bicultural conferences and programs, and the establishment of a Pan-American cultural center and library in Los Angeles. The war years witnessed a rising tide of California racism and xenophobia. Young Hispanics in their flashy zoot suits offered convenient targets for racially-motivated violence by members of the military and blatant prejudice by the public at large. In his capacity as chairman of the Citizens Committee for Latin American Youth (a group appointed by the Los Angeles County Board of Supervisors to improve the living and working conditions of young Hispanics), Ruiz was involved in the defense of members of the 38th Street Club, twenty-two of whom were convicted of criminal conspiracy in the death of Jose Diaz in a 1942 incident which came to be known as the Sleepy Lagoon Case. The Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee, which included such prominent community leaders as Luisa Moreno, Josefina Fierro de Bright, Bert Corona and Carey McWilliams, succeeded in obtaining a reversal of the verdict by the District Court of Appeals in October, 1944, after the defendants had spent two years in prison. Ruiz published his succinct analysis of the juvenile delinquency problem and suggested detailed steps to ameliorate it in "Latin-American Juvenile Delinquency in Los Angeles: Bomb or Bubble!" (Crime Prevention Digest, vol. 1, no. 13, Dec., 1942). With Eduardo Quevedo and others, Ruiz founded the Coordinating Council for Latin American Youth (CCLAY), a loose coalition of youth groups which worked informally in clubs and sports teams to help teenagers improve their economic and educational situations and cooperated with law enforcement and social agencies to prevent juvenile delinquency. Ruiz was active as secretary of, and attorney for, CCLAY from 1941 to 1946. He was also appointed by Governor Earl Warren to the California Committee on Youth in Wartime (later the California Youth Committee) in 1943 and served until 1947. Despite the efforts of CCLAY and similar groups, zoot suiters and servicemen battled in the East Los Angeles barrio in early June, 1943. The press gave sensational front-page coverage to the so-called Pachuco or Zoot Suit Riots and blamed Mexican American youths for the fighting. Authorities, including Los Angeles mayor Fletcher Brown, acted slowly to end the violence. Mexican Americans, Blacks and Filipinos were beaten, and more than 600 were arrested without cause before pressure by the Mexican government and U.S. federal authorities brought an end to the inactivity of mayor Brown and the military police. In 1963 Ruiz joined the Mexican American Political Association (MAPA) which had been formed five years earlier in Phoenix, after the defeat of Democratic candidate Henry P. Lopez in the California secretary of state contest. The founders realized that Mexican Americans could not depend on either major party to champion their interests. The association assumed a more concrete form at a conference in Fresno, California in April, 1960, and Congressman Eduardo Roybal of Los Angeles became its first president. Ruiz became involved at the time of MAPA's incorporation on May 2, 1963, and he helped to draft the by-laws. MAPA was bipartisan and decentralized, with chapters organized within state assembly districts for the purpose of electing Mexican American and sympathetic candidates, registering voters, and sponsoring political education seminars and publications. The membership was predominantly young, urban and middle class. MAPA organized VIVA Kennedy clubs to support John F. Kennedy in the 1960 presidential race, supported an unsuccessful drive to incorporate East Los Angeles as a separate city in 1961, and played a major role in the election of John Moreno and Phillip Soto to the state assembly in 1962. Ruiz assumed responsibility as a member of the MAPA Organizational Committee and the Executive Board; he was also elected legal counsel for the California and Arizona state MAPA organizations. In the mid-1960s he served as publisher and principal financial supporter of the short-lived newspaper The Voice of the Spanish-Speaking People. Although Eduardo Quevedo, Bert Corona and most other members of the MAPA hierarchy were Democrats, Ruiz maintained his membership in the Republican Party. In 1964 he accepted the position of National Chairman, Hispanic Division, of the Republican National Committee during Barry Goldwater's unsuccessful bid for the presidency. From 1965 to 1968 Ruiz served as secretary to the board of directors and as legal counsel to War on Poverty, Inc. This non-profit corporation was founded to stimulate grass-roots community action to address urban and rural poverty and to initiate programs to raise the living standards of low-income families. War on Poverty, Inc. was successful in attracting sizeable grants from the United States Department of Labor to fund the Educational Resources Information Service (1966-1968) and the Manpower Opportunities Project (1966-1968). The former, funded by a grant of $48,000, was designed to help low-income youth in Los Angeles County obtain jobs, loans, and scholarship funds which would allow them to attend college. The Manpower Opportunities Project (MOP), based in Fresno and serving the Stockton, San Jose, San Bernardino, Los Angeles and Fresno areas, was funded by a Department of Labor grant of $400,000. MOP's efforts were aimed toward a demonstration project to provide low-income Hispanics with assistance in job placement and training. Both programs emphasized the need for counseling, higher education, on-the-job training, and placement services in order to reduce the unemployment rate. Neither project was successful in attracting continued financial support after federal funding ceased. In the late 1960s and early 1970s Ruiz served as a member of the board of directors of the Legal Aid Foundation of Los Angeles. In 1972 he authored (and privately printed) Mexican American Legal Heritage in the Southwest; a second edition appeared in 1974. Ruiz's lifelong interest in education and law was recognized by President Richard M. Nixon who appointed him to the United States Commission on Civil Rights (USCCR) in 1970. The Commission, an independent, bipartisan, fact-finding agency created by Congress in 1957, studies legal developments which infringe on citizens' constitutional rights. Although it lacks enforcement powers, it reports its findings directly to Congress and the President. Ruiz was a commissioner-designate when the USCCR released its report "Mexican Americans and the Administration of Justice in the Southwest" in April, 1970. The 135-page document censured police misconduct, underrepresentation of Hispanics on juries and in law enforcement agencies, abuse of bail regulations, and inadequate legal representation of defendants in the five Southwestern states. It proposed eighteen steps for solving these problems. J. Edgar Hoover, chief of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, vigorously defended the FBI against the Commission's critique. Ruiz was instrumental in bringing about the USCCR's investigation into the death of Ruben Salazar, a prominent Los Angeles Times reporter who was killed by police on August 29, 1970 in the aftermath of the Chicano Moratorium Day riots in East Los Angeles. Ruiz's particular interests as a commissioner included police brutality, prison conditions, school desegregation, and bilingual education. He served on the commission for ten years. Manuel Ruiz is married to the former Claudia Scipper; they have one daughter. He maintains a law office on South Spring Street in Los Angeles as he has for more than forty years.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The Manuel Ruiz, Jr. papers support research on such topics as organization of Hispanic communities, discrimination and segregation in housing, employment and schooling, the administration of justice, police-community relations, and juvenile delinquency--each topic important to an understanding of the Mexican American experience in Southern California during and following the Second World War. The collection spans the years 1931 to 1984, with the bulk of the papers dating from 1940 to 1948 and 1963 to 1978. There are almost no records from the decades of the 1930s and 1950s. The majority of the ten linear foot collection consists of organizational records and subject files. There are minutes, agendas, reports, articles, correspondence, notes, statements, newspaper clippings, financial records, by-laws and photographs. The collection is divided into six series: Personal and Biographical Information, Writings of Manuel Ruiz, Jr., Political Files, Organizational Records, Subject Files, and Photographs.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
- SERIES I: PERSONAL AND BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION
  This brief series contains personal correspondence, resumes, Ruiz's notes on several of the organizations whose records are included in this collection (written when the collection was donated to Stanford University Libraries), and miscellany. Among the biographical items are: Ruiz's applications for employment with the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the Civil Service Commission during World War II, correspondence with his long-time friend Eduardo Quevedo pertaining to Ruiz's induction into the Mexican American Political Association in 1963, and the program for the installation of Ruiz as a member of the United States Commission on Civil Rights.
- SERIES II: WRITINGS OF MANUEL RUIZ, JR.
  The second series contains drafts of writings, speeches, articles published in the Los Angeles Daily Journal (a legal newspaper), transcripts of radio programs (1942, 1943), and an oral history interview on Mexican land grants in California (1972). One article of particular interest is "Latin-American Juvenile Delinquency in Los Angeles: Bomb or Bubble!" (Crime Prevention Digest, Vol. 1, no. 13, Dec., 1942), which emphasized Ruiz's concerns and solutions for the problems of Hispanic youth in the wake of the Sleepy Lagoon Murder trial.
- SERIES III: POLITICAL FILES OF MANUEL RUIZ, JR.
  Ruiz was a member of the Republican Party and was involved in the presidential campaigns of both Nelson Rockefeller and Barry Goldwater in 1964. Although Goldwater appointed him National Chairman, Hispanic Division, of the Republican National Committee, there is only a single folder on the campaign. He supported Evelle Younger in his campaigns for public office in Los Angeles and California in the 1960s. The political records include correspondence, reports, notes, campaign ephemera and newsclippings.
- SERIES IV: ORGANIZATIONAL RECORDS
  The fourth series, which is by far the largest of the six, consists of records resulting from Ruiz's participation in numerous community organizations. The series is divided into the following sub-series: Cultura Panamericana, Inc., the Coordinating Council for Latin American Youth, other organizations, 1931-1956, Mexican American Political Association, War on Poverty, Inc., and other organizations, 1964-1969.
  Cultura Panamericana, Inc. was founded in Los Angeles in 1940, and numbered among its members Latin American consular representatives and United States citizens who were interested in cultural exchange among their respective countries. Included in this sub-series are the articles of incorporation and by-laws, correspondence, financial and membership records, printed programs, and the planning documents for an inter-American cultural center and school for Los Angeles. Ruiz was a founder with Eduardo Quevedo of the Coordinating Council for Latin American Youth. The founding documents, correspondence, financial and membership records, minutes, newsclippings, notes and printed programs demonstrate the breadth of issues which CCLAY strove to address. Under CCLAY's auspices, adult and teen-age representatives from many groups dealt with matters such as defense employment, job training, recreational facilities and housing for minorities, police-community relations, and plans for community organizing in the post-war period. CCLAY functioned from 1941 to 1948, and Ruiz served as its secretary and attorney from 1941 to 1946. Other Organizations, 1931-1956 sub-series includes such youth, civil rights and cultural groups as the California Committee on Youth in Wartime, 1943-1945 (later the California Youth Committee, 1945-1947); Circulo Mexicano, 1940-1943; Citizens' Committee for Latin American Youth (to which Ruiz was appointed by the Los Angeles County Board of Supervisors), 1942-1944; Los Angeles County Committee for Interracial Progress, 1943-1946; Los Angeles Youth Project, 1942-1947; Mexican Chamber of Commerce of Los Angeles, 1943-1953; Southern California Council of Inter-American Affairs, 1943-1945; the President's Committee on Fair Employment Practice, 1941-1946; and the Statewide Committee for a California Fair Employment Practices Commission, 1945-1946. Ruiz's membership in the Mexican American Political Association dates from its incorporation in California in 1963. Records from the state organization include by-laws, the constitution, convention programs, correspondence, records of the MAPA Executive Board, rosters, and records pertaining to the newspaper, The Voice of The Spanish-Speaking People, 1965-1966. There are folders on braceros, meetings with Governor Edmund G. (Pat) Brown, civil rights, the Mexican-American Study Project at the University of California at Los Angeles, and the Delano Grape Strike. Records from the regions and chapters are mostly limited to membership rosters, although there are correspondence, newsletters and programs from the chapters in Los Angeles' 40th and 41st assembly districts. The largest of the Organizational Records sub-series is entitled War On Poverty, Inc. Ruiz helped to found this non-profit organization which was established in 1965 for the purpose of initiating programs to aid low-income persons in urban and rural areas. War on Poverty, Inc. was successful in attracting start-up funding from the United States Department of Labor and the Office of Economic Opportunity, and Ruiz, as secretary of the board of directors and legal counsel, was instrumental in negotiating contracts and keeping projects in compliance with government guidelines. There are records from two of these programs, the Educational Resources Information Service and the Manpower Opportunities Project. ERIS was a small-scale, demonstration project operating in Los Angeles, which assisted young people in participating in post-secondary education and job training programs. MOP, headed by Hector Abeytia, offered southern and central Californians job training and placement services. The records from War on Poverty, Inc. and its projects are primarily contracts, correspondence, financial records, minutes and reports. The final sub-series, Other Organizations, 1964-1969, contains single folders on three groups: the Fair Employment Practices Commission, 1964-1969; Neighborhood Youth Corps, 1966-1967; and Youth Opportunities Foundation, 1964-1966. All reflect interests which Ruiz had maintained since his early days as a community organizer in the 1940s.
- SERIES V: SUBJECT FILES
  The fifth series is divided into the following sub-series: Civil Rights; Miscellaneous Subjects, 1933-1957; Mexican Americans and Education; Police-Community Relations; Administration of Justice; and Miscellaneous Subjects, 1967-1977. The Civil Rights section consists of correspondence, reports, and newsclippings concerning racial discrimination, school segregation and legislation about civil rights matters. There is some material pertaining to the Sleepy Lagoon Murder Case and the Zoot Suit Riots (Box 16, folders 5 and 6). Mexican Americans and Education, 1963-1978, contains correspondence, notes, reports and newsclippings pertaining to the university teaching career of Dr. Manuel H. Guerra. As an outspoken critic of discrimination against Mexican Americans in academic hiring and tenure decisions, he either resigned or was released from the University of Southern California, Arizona State University and California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo. Ruiz became his confidant and supporter, and their correspondence and notes from 1963 to 1977 provide insight into the problems experienced by a Mexican American professional some thirty years after Ruiz himself was denied access to employment with an established law firm. The remainder of this sub-section is concerned with the United States Commission on Civil Rights work in the areas of bilingual education and school desegregation. The next sub-series, Police-Community Relations, 1967-1978, is notable for the information it provides on the death of Ruben Salazar, a Los Angeles Times reporter who was killed when struck by a police tear gas container while covering the Chicano Moratorium Day riots in East Los Angeles in August, 1970. At that time, Ruiz was a commissioner-designate of the United States Commission on Civil Rights and was instrumental in convincing the Commission to make an inquiry into Salazar's death. The Commission's report, "Police-Community Relations in East Los Angeles" (1970), and minutes of the Los Angeles County Commission on Human Relations Law Enforcement and Police-Community Relations Committees, 1971-1972, are also located in this sub-series. The treatment of prisoners, especially minorities, was an issue of particular interest to Ruiz. The Administration of Justice sub-series focuses on this topic and on the USCCR's report entitled "Mexican Americans and the Administration of Justice in the Southwest" (1970). There are also newsletters from the Mexican-American Self Help Group at McNeil Island Federal Penitentiary in Washington state (1971-1973), information on the National Prison Project (1973-1974), and Ruiz's correspondence with prison inmates (1969-1971).
- SERIES VI: PHOTOGRAPHS
  There are three group photographs which include Manuel Ruiz, all dating from 1968 to 1977. The photographs of the Los Angeles Public Library, circa 1940, were removed from the Cultura Panamericana, Inc. subseries. Cultura Panamericana considered securing space there for its Latin American library and cultural center.
- SERIES VII: OVERSIZED MATERIALS
  This series contains media archives whose size did not permit their storage among the rest of the collection.
CONTAINER LIST
- SERIES I: PERSONAL AND BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION, 1939-1977
  - Biographical information, 1939-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Acuna-Equal (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Fierro de Bright-Los Angeles Times (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Marion-Romero (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Ruiz-Woman's (Box 1, Folder 5)
- SERIES II: WRITINGS OF MANUEL RUIZ, JR., 1942-1980
  - Drafts of writings and speeches, 1942-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Drafts of writings and speeches, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper articles, Los Angeles Daily Journal, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Transcripts of interviews, 1942; 1943; 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- SERIES III: POLITICAL FILES OF MANUEL RUIZ, JR., 1963-1973
  - Goldwater, Barry, campaign, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "National Roster of Spanish-Surname Elected Officials and Selected Leaders," 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson, campaign, 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Younger, Evelle, campaign, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous political papers, 1960-1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - (for additional political material, see Box 21)
- SERIES IV: ORGANIZATIONAL RECORDS, 1931-1977
  - Subseries A: Cultura Panamericana, Inc. 1940-1944
    - Articles of Incorporation and By-laws, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Mar.-Dec., 1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Jan.-May, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, June, 1941-Oct., 1942 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Mar., 1943-Apr., 1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Cultural Center, requests for funds, (photographs moved to Box 20, Folder 11) 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Financial records, 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Membership rosters, address lists, ca. 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Pan-American School, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Programs, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subseries B: Coordinating Council for Latin American Youth, 1941-1948
    - Articles of Incorporation, Constitution and By-laws, Statement of Purpose, 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, out-going, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, out-going, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, out-going, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, out-going, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, out-going, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, out-going, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, in-coming, Aguilar-County (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, in-coming, Diaz-Huerta (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, in-coming, Inter-American-Quevedo (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, in-coming, Ramos-Young (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Defense employment and job training for aliens, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Defense housing for aliens, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 3)